It’s true, isn’t it?
When we look at this prophecy
in the book of Micah,
ミカ書は興奮を誘います
it’s very exciting
because it portrays to us
その預言が 現在 神の民の間で
生じていることを描いているからです
what’s actually happening
among God’s people today.
We know that although
in the new world
新しい世で 神の民の間に—
素晴らしい一致が見られるということを
わたしたちは知っていますが—
there will be a tremendous unity
displayed by God’s people,
chapter 4 of Micah
ミカ 4章は まさに今 起きていて—
is actually portraying  what’s happening now,
わたしたちにもかかわりのあることを
描いています
and we’re involved with this.
We know that because
in verse 5 it says
5節には その一致と同時に
存在する状況について—
that at the same time
that this unity would be evident:
“All the peoples will walk,
each in the name of its god.”
“もろもろの民は皆 それぞれ—”
“自分たちの神の名によって歩む”
とあるからです
Well, that’s not talking
about the new world, is it?
It’s talking about the time
we are living in now.
これは新しい世には当てはまりません
今の時代のことを言っていますね
Well, what is it that helps all
of Jehovah’s Witnesses worldwide
世界中のエホバの証人を
これほどまでに一致させ—
to be so united and not to be involved
with the wars of this world?
世の紛争にかかわらないように
させているものは何でしょうか？
Well, one of the things that helps us
is our Christian neutrality.
1つは クリスチャンの中立の立場です
What do we mean by neutrality?
中立とは何でしょうか？
We mean not taking sides
in political issues.
政治問題において—
いずれの側にも付かない
ということです
Of course, we take sides
with Jehovah and the Kingdom,
エホバとその王国は支持しますが—
but with regard to worldly political debates
and issues that arise,
世の政治論争や政治問題に関しては
どちらの側も支持しないのです
we don’t take sides.
Why is this so important?
それが重要なのはなぜでしょうか？
Well, let’s turn our Bibles
to Revelation chapter 13.
啓示 13章を開きましょう
Revelation 13:16, 17,
13章 16, 17節です
and here it tells us:
“それは すべての人 すなわち
小なる者と大なる者—”
“It puts under compulsion all people
—the small and the great,
“the rich and the poor,
the free and the slaves
“富んだ者と貧しい者
自由な者と奴隷を強制して—”
“—that these should be marked
on their right hand or on their forehead,
“その右手や額に印を受けさせ—”
“and that nobody can buy or sell
except a person having the mark,
“また その印 つまり野獣の名—”
“もしくはその名の数字を
持つ者以外には—”
the name of the wild beast
or the number of its name.”
“だれも売り買いできないようにする”
What’s the point of this verse?
この聖句の要点は何でしょうか？
Well, of course,
we will look forward to seeing
この聖句がどのように成就するか—
how this may
turn out in the future
神の民に
どんな圧力がかかってくるかは—
and what pressure is put
on God’s people at that time.
将来明らかになるでしょう
But even now,
we see the principle here
しかし 今でさえ
政治体制がわたしたちに—
that the political system is wanting
to put its mark on us,
印を付けたがっている
ということは明らかです
mentally as well as physically.
行動においても 考えにおいてもです
So we see the forehead
as well as the hand being involved.
“右手や額に”
と言われているからです
So we need to be absolutely certain
that we remain neutral
ですから わたしたちは 政治に
直接関与しないのはもちろんのこと—
with regard to political issues
in the world,
not only by
not being involved actively
気持ちの上でもどちらかの側に
付くことのないようにして—
in the political issues
中立を保つよう
注意深くあるべきです
but also mentally not allowing
ourselves to take sides.
What are some of the things
that perhaps could erode our neutrality?
わたしたちの中立が徐々に崩れていく
ということもあります
Well, maybe we could mention
three things this morning.
今日は３つの原因を考えましょう
One is the propaganda
that the world puts forward.
最初に この世のプロパガンダ
—宣伝— です
Now, we have seen what the media says
about Jehovah’s Witnesses, haven’t we?
時々メディアが
ゆがめられた報道をするため—
How distorted some of their reports are
人々はエホバの証人に対し
マイナスのイメージを持つようになります
and how they can paint
a negative picture with regard to us.
Well, should we expect
that they are neutral
他の報道に関しても同じことが
あり得るのではないでしょうか？
with regard to other events
that they report on,
particularly when there are conflicts
between two nations?
二国間が対立している場合は
特にそう言えます
The media
in one particular nation may promote
一方の国のメディアは相手国に関して—
certain ideas about the other nation.
ある種のイメージを
持たせようとするかもしれません
We may be affected by that.
We may be surprised perhaps
政治イデオロギーの異なる国を
実際に旅行してみると—
to visit some other countries
that have a different political ideology
メディアが報道していたものと
実際の様子が違うことに—
and be surprised to see
how things perhaps are a little different
驚くことがあります
in that country to how it’s portrayed
by the media in our country.
So we need to be careful
not to be influenced
ですから 世の宣伝
特にメディアの報道に—
by the propaganda of this world,
簡単に影響されないよう
注意する必要があります
particularly media reports and so on.
What’s another thing perhaps
that could cause us
中立の立場を危うくさせる
別の要素を考えましょう
to lose a measure of neutrality?
Sporting events.
スポーツイベントです
Sometimes sporting events
are able to achieve
スポーツイベントは人々の間に
国家主義をあおることがあります
certain goals
with regard to nationalism.
多くのスポーツイベントでは
国歌が歌われます
We see the national anthem
being played at many of these events.
何年も前のこと
別の国にいた時—
It reminds me many years ago
when I was in a different country,
友人がわたしにスポーツイベントを
録画してほしいと頼んできました
a friend of mine asked me
to record a certain sporting event.
あまり関心はなかったのですが—
I wasn’t particularly
interested in the event,
友人の頼みでしたので 録画しました
but because he made this request,
I recorded it.
特に 最後の10分は—
確実に録画できるよう
慎重に行ないました
And, of course, I wanted to make sure
that I got the last ten minutes of it.
その部分を録画し損なって—
I thought our friendship
may be strained
友情にひびが入っては大変だ
と思ったからです
if I didn’t get
the actual last part of the game.
それで
観戦することになったのですが—
When I watched it,
it was absolutely exciting
これが大変エキサイティングで
スリリングな終盤でした
—nail-biting finish.
Well, after the brother
gave me back the videotape,
彼がビデオテープを
返してくれた時に—
I thought maybe
some of the other brothers
このイベントが好きな他の兄弟も
見たいかもしれないと思い—
who would be interested
in this sporting event
テープは消去せず 何人かに
見たいかどうか尋ねてみました
may want to have it
rather than just wipe the tape.
So I offered it to several,
and each one of them said to me:
ところが皆 “いや やめとくよ—”
“No thanks.
“うちが勝ったんだったら
見てもいいけど” と言いました
If we had won,
perhaps it would be different.”
Now, what was the problem?
わたしはこう聞きました
As I said to them,
“観戦するのはプレーを楽しむため？
それともどちらかを応援するため？”
“Were you watching the game
or were you taking sides?”
An interesting concept,
というのは このゲームでは—
because here
two different nations were involved.
2つのナショナルチームが
戦っていたからです
So we have to be careful
that even sporting events
ですから スポーツ観戦であっても—
国家主義的な感情が
わき上がることのないように—
don’t stir up within us
certain nationalistic feelings,
注意する必要があります
and perhaps we could take sides
with regard to certain events.
自国を応援してしまうというのは
あり得ることだからです
The third area that perhaps
could erode our neutrality:
中立の立場を崩されかねない
3つ目の分野は—
the political promises being made,
particularly at election time.
政治家のする約束—
特に選挙時の公約です
Perhaps one of the candidates
is from our ethnic background
自分と同じ民族の人や—
自分と同性の人が
立候補するかもしれません
or perhaps
is the same gender as we are.
When we look at the political situation
these days with many elections,
最近の選挙は
政治というよりは—
エンターテインメントという感じです
it seems to be more in the form
of entertainment than anything else,
with music
and very colorful characters.
音楽やカラフルなマスコットが
目立ちます
But if we were
to say in our heart,
心の中で
“こんな人に当選してほしくないな”—
‘I hope that idiot
doesn’t get into power,’
などと思い始めたとしたら—
are we neutral?
それは中立と言えるでしょうか？
Or worse still, if we say,
もっと悪いことに
“あの人が当選したらいいのに”—
‘I hope the other person
gets into power,’
などと思い始めたら大変です
well, we need
to be careful, don’t we?
I remember many years ago
as a young pioneer in Australia,
わたしは若い頃 オーストラリアで
開拓奉仕をしていましたが—
I was facing
the conscription issue
徴兵の問題に直面しました
—the national call-up
for the military.
At that time,
the Vietnam War was being fought.
ベトナム戦争の真っただ中でした
And then there was
an election in Australia.
時を同じくして
オーストラリアでは選挙がありました
And at that time, the party
that was trying to get into power
当時 政権を取ろうとしていた政党が
徴兵廃止を公約に掲げていました
said that if they got into power,
they would abolish conscription.
So now that affected me personally.
わたしも個人的に影響を受けました
I remember how hard it was sitting there
watching the election results,
選挙結果を見ながら—
その政党に勝ってほしい
という気持ちを抑えるのは大変でした
not to say in my heart,
‘I hope they get in.’
And then, when they got in,
not to say, ‘Yes!’
実際 その政党が政権を取った時には
やった！と言いそうになりました
You see, if we personally are affected
by some of these political promises,
このように政治公約を
気持ちの上で支持してしまうなら—
we may violate our neutrality.
中立ではいられなくなります
So brothers and sisters,
let’s work hard at remembering
それでは 兄弟たち—
わたしたちはこの世のものではないことを
しっかりと銘記しましょう
that we’re no part of this world.
We support the best government
that could ever rule this earth.
わたしたちが支持する政府は—
最善の仕方で
この地を支配することができるのです
And by doing so,
we will keep our neutrality,
そのようにして 中立を保ち
一致を保っていきましょう
and we will keep our unity.